A Guide to the Population Council records, Accession 1, RG 1 FA210
Rockefeller Archive Center
Population Council records, Accession 1, RG 1
1952-1966
Rockefeller Archive Center
Population Council
FA210
48.88 Cubic Feet
Biographical/Historical note
The Population Council was founded by John D. Rockefeller 3rd in 1952 to undertake "significant activities in the broad field of population." Its goal has been to bring about a reduction in the number of births that occur in the world. In Its early years, the business of the Population Council was conducted by a Demographic Division and a Biomedical Division. Through its Demographic Division, the Council sought to document what it conceived to be an overpopulation problem threatening many areas of the world. To accomplish this purpose, the Division facilitated research on the economic, social, and psychological factors which affect the growth and decline of human population. This Council-assisted research effort was conducted not only by staff of the Demographic Division but also by other institutions and scholars, some of whom received Council grants and fellowships and some of whom received informal advice and consultation on how to design and execute studies.
The Biomedical Division, which, beginning in 1959, occupied a laboratory at The Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research (now The Rockefeller University), has conducted pure and applied research on plant, animal, and human reproductive physiology and on the development, the physiological action, and the safety and effectiveness of contraceptive methods. The Council facilitated similar types of medical research by non-Council scientists at other institutions by giving grants and fellowships for such research. The Council's biomedical research and its support for research by non-Council scientists were instrumental in the development of the modern intrauterine coil and the birth control pill.
In about 1960, the scope of Population Council activities expanded. The Council began to render practical and technical aid to foreign nations. Beginning in that year, the Demographic Division, in addition to supervising research, became involved in Pakistan's family planning program, extending practical and technical aid in organizing and running a national family planning program. By 1964 the Council's Demographic Division had assisted in organizing family planning programs in South Korea, Taiwan, Thailand, Tunisia, and Turkey. In that year, the Council created the Technical Assistance Division. This division, in ensuing years, continued the assistance of the Council in the countries where it had already become involved and also helped start and run programs in India, Morocco, the Philippines, and Puerto Rico.
An underlying aim of the Council's grant programs has been to encourage the development and growth of institutions that would promote family planning programs. To this end, the Council has given grants and advice to various universities and research centers for starting and upgrading programs for demographic and biomedical training and research programs; has assisted the United Nations to set up and expand regional Demographic Training and Research Centres in Bombay, India, Santiago, Chile, and Cairo, Egypt; has worked with the Ford Foundation on family planning programs in Pakistan, India, and North Africa.
In addition to rendering technical aid and sponsoring research, the Council has undertaken several complementary public relations efforts. To reach the general populations of the United States and of foreign nations, Council officers have worked to inform the mass media about population issues and to encourage magazine articles, movies, and books dealing with population matters. Council officers and representatives have also made trips and prepared reports to convince various foreign government leaders of the importance and the desirability of promulgating family planning programs. In addition, Council officers participated in and helped organize and finance conferences for demographers and medical scientists active in population work.
The Population Council has obtained its financial support through large contributions. The Ford and Rockefeller Foundations and the Rockefeller Brothers Fund have been the principal institutional supporters of the Council. John D. Rockefeller 3rd has been the single most significant individual backer of the Council.
Arrangement
Accession I is arranged in five series.
Scope and Contents note
The records of the Population Council document its day-to-day operation as an organization that, among other activities, evaluated and administered grants, sponsored conferences of scholars in the field of population control, and provided advice to individuals, private institutions, and governments concerned with population. There is some material relating to major policy decisions of the Council. There are also letters and reports from scientists involved in medical research and from Council staff members and representatives involved in family planning activities abroad.
The Council records are divided into two accessions. Accession 1, most of which is dated before 1967, consists of material received by the Archive Center in September, 1976. Accession 2, most of which is dated after 1966, consists primarily of material received by the Center in April, 1977.
The records of Accession 1 and Accession 2 have been kept separate because the Council evidently employed different filing systems in each of the two units and because the existence of the different filing systems sheds light on the manner in which the Council was organized and run. The use of this approach has meant that the files are organized in such a way that material relating to a given topic may appear in several different parts of the collection under either identical names or titles, or under different names or titles. For example, in the case of some institutions whose proper names are in a foreign language, records may have been filed under both the foreign name and under an English rendering of the name. The files also contain many carbon copies and there is duplication throughout the collection, so that copies of the same item may appear in several places.
To conduct a thorough search for records on a given topic, it is essential to look for material in as many different sections of the collection and under as many different names or titles as possible. For example, material relating to a given organization may be listed under the name of the organization, under the name of important figures in the organization, or under a title reflecting a study or type of work done by the organization.
File Plan note
Former Classification: IV 3B 04.
Separated Material
Non-textual materials (charts, maps, objects, photographs) have been separated from the written records. Cross-reference sheets appear among the written records showing that non-textual items have been removed. Photographs are filed as a separate series.
Custodial History note
The description of the records of the Population Council was written in 1978 when the described records, designated as Accession 1, were initially processed and opened to researchers. In accordance with the criteria developed at that time, certain documents and files were closed from scholarly access.
In January 2001, those criteria were reevaluated. Subsequent to the review of all the closed files, new guidelines for the continued closure of Accession 1 records were established. The revised criteria specified that continued closure was warranted only for records that revealed names of patients or participants in medical studies. Additionally, all personnel files were to remain closed.
The new, less stringent closure guidelines allowed for the opening of dozens of files that had previously been closed to research. These files are easily identifiable throughout the collection. The word "CLOSED," which had been written in red pencil at the top of the folder, now has a red line through it. Furthermore, these previously closed folders have been stamped "Open as of July 2001."
Those files that have remained closed are no longer intermingled with the open records. They are, instead, filed at the end of Accession I in boxes 129 and 130.
Related Materials
John D. Rockefeller 3rd papers Ford Foundation records John D. Rockefeller 3rd Associates: Joan Dunlop papers Mary Kritz papers George Zeidenstein papers
Other Finding Aids
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) or audiovisual material (audio cassettes, VHS, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Cell and biomolecular sciences; Economic development; Sociology; Family planning; Economics; Physiology; Birth control; Biology -- Research; Federal government -- United States; United States; Population; Fertility; Life sciences; Overpopulation; Maternal health services
- Accession 1, 1
  - General File, 1952-1966; 1
    Scope and Contents note
    Alphabetical file which consists of correspondence, memoranda, and reports. The documents relate to the administration and funding of the Population Council, the Council's publicizing of the problem of overpopulation, Council sponsorship of or consultation on medical and demographic research projects, and Council involvement with various family planning programs. Important files include those for the Ad Hoc Philosophy Committee, the Ford Foundation, the Rockefeller Foundation, the Rockefeller Brothers Fund.
    Arrangement note
    Arranged so that large amounts of material concerning a given person, institution, or subject are stored together in one or more folders. Such material is arranged in chronological order, and the folders appear throughout the General File in appropriate alphabetical order. For each letter of the alphabet, a general folder has been used for small amounts of material filed under that letter. Material in the folders is filed alphabetically. The general folder(s) for each letter precede(s) all folders that are filed under the letter.
    File Plan note
    Former Classification: IV 3B 04.2
    General
    Indexing to the General File is provided by FA775 Population Council records, Index, Series 1: General File Index, 1952-1961.
    - A, 1953-1957 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
    - Ad Hoc Philosophy Committee
      - Kirk, Dudley, 1948-1957 (Box 1, Folder 3-8)
      - Meetings 1-5 - Correspondence and Summaries, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - Meeting 6 - Correspondence, Discussion Papers, and Summaries, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - Meeting 6 - Correspondence, Discussion Papers and Summaries, 1956-1957 (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - Meeting 7 - Correspondence and Discussion Papers, 1956-1957 (Box 2, Folder 12)
      - Meeting 8 - Correspondence and Discussion Papers, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 13)
      - Meetings 1-8 - Summary - Notes and Worksheets (Box 2, Folder 14)
      - Meetings 1-8 - Summary - Corrected Copy (Box 2, Folder 15)
      - Meetings 1-8 - Summary and Comments on Summary - A-N, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 16)
      - Meetings 1-8 - Summary and Comments on Summary - P-Z, 1957-1958 (Box 2, Folder 17)
      - Physiology of Reproduction - Conference, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 18-19)
      - Publication - Population: An International Dilemma, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 20)
      - Publication - Population: An International Dilemma - Acknowledgments of Copies, 1958-1959 (Box 3, Folder 21-22)
      - Publication - Population: An International Dilemma - Correspondence Concerning Distribution, 1958-1961 (Box 3, Folder 23)
      - Publication - Population: An International Dilemma - Correspondence with Committee Members and Discussants, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 24)
      - Publication - Population: An International Dilemma - Correspondence with Princeton University Press, 1957-1959 (Box 3, Folder 25)
      - Publication - Population: An International Dilemma - (Working Title, "An American Looks at Population") Drafts, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 26)
      - Publication - Population: An International Dilemma - Proof Sheets (Box 3, Folder 27)
      - Publication - Population: An International Dilemma - Proof Sheets, Index (Box 3, Folder 28)
      - Publication - Population: An International Dilemma - Reviews and Testimonials, 1958-1960 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Administration
      - Biomedical Division - Biomedical Advisory Committee - Grants, 1963-1966 (Box 3, Folder 30)
      - Biomedical Division - Book and Equipment Fund, 1962-1965 (Box 3, Folder 31)
      - Biomedical Division - Committee on Intrauterine Contraceptive Devices, 1964-1966 (Box 3, Folder 32)
      - Biomedical Division - Consultants - Southam, Anna L., 1964-1966 (Box 3, Folder 33-34)
      - Biomedical Division - Correspondence, Reports, Studies, 1960-1966 (Box 4, Folder 35-36)
      - Biomedical Division - Lawrence, Kenneth A., 1960-1966 (Box 4, Folder 37)
      - Biomedical Division - Segal, Sheldon, 1963-1966 (Box 4, Folder 38-39)
      - Demographic Division, 1957-1966 (Box 4, Folder 40-42)
      - Demographic Division - Book, Equipment and Publication Fund, 1965-1966 (Box 4, Folder 43)
      - Demographic Division - Demographic Advisory Committee, 1953-1957 (Box 4, Folder 44)
      - Demographic Division - Training and Recruitment of Demographers, 1962-1965 (Box 4, Folder 45-46)
      - Technical Assistance Division - Book, Equipment and Publication Fund, 1965-1967 (Box 4, Folder 47-48)
      - Technical Assistance Division - Correspondence, Reports, Studies, 1963-1966 (Box 4, Folder 49)
    - Africa
      - Boston University Seminar on African Studies, 1957-1961 (Box 4, Folder 50-51)
      - Grant Authorized - Lorimer, Frank, 1957-1959 (Box 4, Folder 52)
      - Grant Authorized - Lorimer, Frank, 1958-1959 (Box 5, Folder 53)
      - Grant Authorized - Paris Seminar on African Demography, 1959 1958-1961 (Box 5, Folder 54-55)
    - American Humanist Association, 1957 (Box 5, Folder 56)
    - American University, 1954-1960 (Box 5, Folder 57-62)
    - Australia, 1954-1958 (Box 5, Folder 63)
    - Australia, 1958-1959 (Box 6, Folder 64-65)
    - B, 1954-1958 (Box 6, Folder 66)
    - Barclay, George, 1955-1959 1967 (Box 6, Folder 67-68)
    - Book Reviews, 1954 (Box 6, Folder 69)
    - British West Indies - Jamaica Family Life Study, 1955-1957 (Box 6, Folder 70)
    - C, 1953-1959 (Box 6, Folder 71-73)
    - Caribbean Commission, 1956-1957 (Box 6, Folder 74)
    - Carnegie Corporation of New York, 1953-1959 (Box 6, Folder 75)
    - Catholic Church, 1953-1957 (Box 7, Folder 76-77)
    - Columbia University, 1954-1959 (Box 7, Folder 78)
    - Conservation Foundation, 1953-1959 (Box 7, Folder 79-80)
    - Contraceptive Information Center (Proposed), 1956-1957 (Box 7, Folder 81-82)
    - Controlled Fertility Research Centre - de Laszlo, Henry, 1953-1954 (Box 7, Folder 83-84)
    - Council on Economic and Cultural Affairs, 1954-1958 (Box 7, Folder 85-88)
    - D, 1954-1960 (Box 8, Folder 89)
    - Dallas Council of World Affairs, 1960-1961 (Box 8, Folder 90)
    - E, 1954-1958 (Box 8, Folder 91-92)
    - F, 1953-1957 (Box 8, Folder 93-94)
    - Fomos Tablets, 1955-1957 (Box 8, Folder 95-96)
    - Ford Foundation
      - General Material, 1953-1960 (Box 8, Folder 97-99)
      - General Material, 1954-1964 (Box 9, Folder 100)
      - Baumgartner, Leona - India Trip, 1955-1956 (Box 9, Folder 101-102)
      - Committee on Migration, 1958-1959 (Box 9, Folder 103-104)
      - Grant to Population Council, 1962-1967 (Box 9, Folder 105-106)
      - Grant to Population Council for Latin American Demographic Center (CELADE) (Chile), 1961-1965 (Box 9, Folder 107)
      - Grant to Population Council for Pakistan, 1964-1966 (Box 9, Folder 108)
      - Grant to Population Council for Pakistan - Agreements and Reports, 1960-1965 (Box 9, Folder 109)
      - Grant to Population Council for Tunisia, 1963-1966 (Box 9, Folder 110)
      - Grant to University of Chile - (Population Council Acted as Purchasing Agent), 1963-1966 (Box 9, Folder 111-112)
    - G, 1953-1959 (Box 9, Folder 113-114)
    - Grant Applications
      - Human Betterment Association, 1952-1957 (Box 9, Folder 115)
      - Planned Parenthood Federation of America, Incorporated, 1953 (Box 9, Folder 116)
      - Stellenbosch University, 1957 (Box 9, Folder 117)
      - University of Chicago, 1957 (Box 9, Folder 118)
      - University of Puerto Rico, 1957 (Box 9, Folder 119)
      - A-Z, 1954-1957 (Box 10, Folder 120-121)
      - A-Z - Rejections, 1953-1955 (Box 10, Folder 122)
      - Grants and Fellowships - List, 1953-1956 (Box 10, Folder 123)
    - Grants Authorized
      - Albert Einstein College of Medicine, 1967-1968 (Box 10, Folder 124)
      - All India Institute of Hygiene and Public Health, 1954-1957 (Box 10, Folder 125-126)
      - All India Institute of Hygiene and Public Health - Reports on Contraceptive Research, 1957 (Box 10, Folder 127)
      - American Eugenics Society, 1955-1958 (Box 10, Folder 128)
      - American Society of Human Genetics - First International Conference of Human Genetics, 1955-1956 (Box 10, Folder 129)
      - Banaras Hindu University, 1961-1962 (Box 10, Folder 130)
      - Bureau of the Census (United States), 1955-1956 (Box 10, Folder 131)
      - Carnegie Institute of Washington - Bishop, David and Katsh, Seymour, 1955-1958 (Box 10, Folder 132)
      - Centro Latinoamericano de Demografia (CELADE) Chile, 1958-1961 (Box 10, Folder 133-134)
      - Cold Spring Harbor - Symposium, 1957 (Box 10, Folder 135)
      - Columbia University - Doctors' Attitudes Survey, 1952-1965 (Box 10, Folder 136-138)
      - Columbia University - Doctors' Attitudes Survey, 1956 1963 (Box 11, Folder 139)
      - Columbia University - Gartler, Stanley - Twin Study, 1955-1957 (Box 11, Folder 140)
      - Columbia University - Intrauterine Devices Studies, 1964 (Box 11, Folder 141)
      - Columbia University - Jaffe, Abram - Puerto Rico Study, 1954-1958 (Box 11, Folder 142-143)
      - Columbia University - Sutton, Constance, 1957-1960 (Box 11, Folder 144)
      - Committee on Intrauterine Contraceptive Devices, 1964-1965 (Box 11, Folder 145-146)
      - Commonwealth Scientific and Industrial Research Organization, 1958-1962 (Box 11, Folder 147)
      - Conservation Foundation - Stycos, Joseph, 1957 1959 (Box 11, Folder 148)
      - Cornell University - Stycos, Joseph, 1957-1961 (Box 11, Folder 149-150)
      - Cornell University Medical School - Medical Genetics Conference, 1958-1959 (Box 11, Folder 151)
      - Dartmouth College - Gutman Study, 1954-1956 (Box 11, Folder 152-153)
      - Durand, John, 1956-1957 (Box 11, Folder 154)
      - Egypt, 1955-1958 (Box 11, Folder 155)
      - Genetics Society of America, 1957-1958 (Box 11, Folder 156)
      - Hamburg University, 1957-1961 (Box 11, Folder 157)
      - Harvard University, 1958-1959 (Box 11, Folder 158)
      - Harvard University Medical School - Sturgis, Somers and Velardo, Joseph, 1955 (Box 11, Folder 159)
      - Hayashi, Motoyuki, 1961 (Box 11, Folder 160)
      - Hebrew University (Israel) - Muhsam, H. V., 1959-1964 (Box 11, Folder 161)
      - Institut Franais Afrique (Senegal) - Dakar Mortality Study, 1961-1963 1967 (Box 11, Folder 162-163)
      - Institut Pasteur (France), 1961 1966 (Box 11, Folder 164)
      - Institute of Human Biology - Clark, Philip, 1955 (Box 12, Folder 165-166)
      - Institute of Population Problems (Japan), 1961-1963 1965 (Box 12, Folder 167-168)
      - Institute of Population Problems (Japan) "New Life Movement" Publication, 1960-1963 (Box 12, Folder 169-170)
      - Instituto de Medicina Experimental (Chile), 1958 1961 (Box 12, Folder 171)
      - Inter American Association of Civil Registration, 1960-1961 (Box 12, Folder 172)
      - International Planned Parenthood Federation, 1958-1961 (Box 12, Folder 173)
      - International Planned Parenthood Federation - Travel Grants, 1958-1962 (Box 12, Folder 174-175)
      - International Statistical Institute - Brazil Meeting, 1955 (Box 12, Folder 176)
      - Iowa State University - Witschi, Emil, 1962 (Box 12, Folder 177)
      - Keio University (Japan) - Ojima and Ando, 1955 (Box 12, Folder 178)
      - Krooth, Robert S., 1954-1957 (Box 12, Folder 179)
      - Kyushu University (Japan), 1956-1963 (Box 12, Folder 180)
      - Loyola College - Gibbons, William J., 1954-1958 (Box 12, Folder 181)
      - Margaret Sanger Research Bureau - Hartman, Carl G., 1961 (Box 12, Folder 182)
      - Medical Travel Grants, 1955-1956 (Box 12, Folder 183)
      - Meharry Medical College - Sharpley, Robert H., 1962 (Box 12, Folder 184)
      - Meiji Gakuin University (Japan), 1961 (Box 12, Folder 185-186)
      - Michigan State University - Hill, Mozell, 1961-1964 (Box 12, Folder 187-188)
      - Milbank Memorial Fund - 1956 Fertility Study, 1956-1960 (Box 12, Folder 189)
      - Miscellaneous Fellowships, 1961 (Box 12, Folder 190)
      - National Research Council - Taeuber, Irene, 1953-1954 (Box 12, Folder 191)
      - National Science Development Board (Philippines) - Thompson, Warren, 1959-1963 (Box 13, Folder 192-194)
      - National Taiwan University, 1956-1957 (Box 13, Folder 195)
      - National Taiwan University - Chen, Shao-hsing, 1957-1959 (Box 13, Folder 196-197)
      - New York University - Bellevue Medical Center, 1956 (Box 13, Folder 198)
      - Pakistan, Government of, Central Statistical Office, 1961-1963 (Box 13, Folder 199-200)
      - Pakistan, Government of, Ministry of Health Corsa, Leslie, 1962 (Box 13, Folder 201)
      - Pakistan Institute of Development Economics, 1959-1964 (Box 13, Folder 202-203)
      - Pakistan Statistical Association, 1962 (Box 13, Folder 204)
      - Population Investigation Committee (England), 1954-1958 (Box 13, Folder 205)
      - Population Reference Bureau, 1954-1958 (Box 13, Folder 206-207)
      - Population Research and Training Center (University of Chicago), 1954-1957 (Box 13, Folder 208)
      - Population Studies Center - Taiwan, 1961 (Box 13, Folder 209)
      - Princeton University, 1954-1962 (Box 13, Folder 210)
      - Princeton University - Clairin, Remy, 1961-1962 (Box 13, Folder 211)
      - Purshottam, Natesaier, 1954-1955 (Box 13, Folder 212)
      - Radiumstationen (Denmark), 1961 (Box 14, Folder 213)
      - Schmidt, Stanwood S., 1955 (Box 14, Folder 214)
      - Scripps Foundation, 1953-1956 (Box 14, Folder 215)
      - Scripps Foundation - Whelpton, Pascal K., 1953-1954 (Box 14, Folder 216-217)
      - Seton Hall University College of Medicine and Dentistry, 1961-1962 (Box 14, Folder 218)
      - Southwest Foundation for Research and Education, 1955-1956 (Box 14, Folder 219)
      - Southwest Foundation for Research and Education, 1958-1960 (Box 14, Folder 220)
      - Stanford University, 1959-1965 (Box 14, Folder 221)
      - State Institute of Human Genetics (Sweden), 1957-1958 (Box 14, Folder 222)
      - State University of New York - Lippes, Jack -Travel, 1964 (Box 14, Folder 223-224)
      - Stockholm Conference - International Union for the Scientific Study of Population and International Statistical Institute, 1957 (Box 14, Folder 225)
      - Unitarian Service Committee, 1953-1956 (Box 14, Folder 226-230)
      - United Nations - Athens Seminar on Population of Southern European Countries, 1958 (Box 14, Folder 231)
      - United Nations - Financial Reports, 1960-1966 (Box 14, Folder 232)
      - United Nations - Sanghvi, L. D., 1957-1958 (Box 14, Folder 233)
      - United Nations Demographic Training and Research Centre (Bombay), 1956-1957 (Box 15, Folder 234)